<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-09T13:13:57+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DuckDB Labs</title><subtitle>DuckDB Labs provides services around the DuckDB in-process OLAP data management system directly from its main developers.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Announcing the Hydra Partnership</title><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/08/28/hydra-partnership.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Announcing the Hydra Partnership" /><published>2024-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/08/28/hydra-partnership</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/08/28/hydra-partnership.html"><![CDATA[<p>DuckDB Labs is excited to announce that we are going to be working with <a href="https://www.hydra.so/">Hydra</a> in the coming years to build DuckDB-Powered PostgreSQL for real-time apps and analytics development. DuckDB Labs has entered a long-term strategic partnership with Hydra to enrich and extend the DuckDB ecosystem. Joseph Sciarrino and his co-founder, Jonathan Dance “JD” helped pioneer the fusion of columnar analytics with transactional RDBMS, raising the bar of what’s possible with Postgres, which is why we are confident to join them in this endeavor.</p>

<p>Our collaboration with Hydra revolves around <a href="https://github.com/duckdb/pg_duckdb">pg_duckdb</a>, an open-source (MIT licensed) program that embeds DuckDB’s state-of-the-art analytics engine and features within Postgres. pg_duckdb is meant for developing high-performance applications and analytics with any new or existing Postgres database. We’ve observed software engineers increasingly embedding powerful analytics directly into their applications. These applications tend to require both greater access to disparate data sources and sub-second response times. We believe pg_duckdb will serve these use-cases nicely by overcoming Postgres’ known limitations in analytical processing.</p>

<p>The Hydra team has graciously donated the pg_duckdb repository to the DuckDB Foundation to ensure the project remains open-source and free of conflict. We applaud and share Joseph &amp; JD’s belief in the necessity and long-term benefits of creating an open-source data foundation as the bedrock of future work. pg_duckdb’s continued development is driven in collaboration with Hydra and <a href="https://motherduck.com/">MotherDuck</a> as both companies share an exciting vision for the role of DuckDB in application development.</p>

<p>Hydra joins DuckDB Labs’ excellent lineup of partners that includes <a href="https://motherduck.com/">MotherDuck</a>, <a href="https://voltrondata.com/">Voltron Data</a>, and others. DuckDB Labs is not funded by venture capital, its sole owners are the people in the founding team. All our revenue comes from partnerships where our partners employ DuckDB in mission-critical roles and contract with DuckDB Labs for close and long-term development collaboration. This allows DuckDB Labs to focus on <a href="https://duckdb.org/2024/06/03/announcing-duckdb-100">pushing boundaries</a> in the DuckDB software project without chasing exponential growth in sales.</p>

<p>While consulting alone is a viable business model for open-source companies, it does not scale well. To address this, DuckDB Labs has acquired shares in Hydra, which connects their success with ours. This way, DuckDB Labs’ founding team joins in the financial success of our partners while allowing us to focus on the technical challenges as an artisanal database company.</p>

<p>We welcome all contributions and support to <a href="https://github.com/duckdb/pg_duckdb">pg_duckdb</a>, large and small as pg_duckdb works towards its first release.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDB Labs is excited to announce that we are going to be working with Hydra in the coming years to build DuckDB-Powered PostgreSQL for real-time apps and analytics development. DuckDB Labs has entered a long-term strategic partnership with Hydra to enrich and extend the DuckDB ecosystem. Joseph Sciarrino and his co-founder, Jonathan Dance “JD” helped pioneer the fusion of columnar analytics with transactional RDBMS, raising the bar of what’s possible with Postgres, which is why we are confident to join them in this endeavor. Our collaboration with Hydra revolves around pg_duckdb, an open-source (MIT licensed) program that embeds DuckDB’s state-of-the-art analytics engine and features within Postgres. pg_duckdb is meant for developing high-performance applications and analytics with any new or existing Postgres database. We’ve observed software engineers increasingly embedding powerful analytics directly into their applications. These applications tend to require both greater access to disparate data sources and sub-second response times. We believe pg_duckdb will serve these use-cases nicely by overcoming Postgres’ known limitations in analytical processing. The Hydra team has graciously donated the pg_duckdb repository to the DuckDB Foundation to ensure the project remains open-source and free of conflict. We applaud and share Joseph &amp; JD’s belief in the necessity and long-term benefits of creating an open-source data foundation as the bedrock of future work. pg_duckdb’s continued development is driven in collaboration with Hydra and MotherDuck as both companies share an exciting vision for the role of DuckDB in application development. Hydra joins DuckDB Labs’ excellent lineup of partners that includes MotherDuck, Voltron Data, and others. DuckDB Labs is not funded by venture capital, its sole owners are the people in the founding team. All our revenue comes from partnerships where our partners employ DuckDB in mission-critical roles and contract with DuckDB Labs for close and long-term development collaboration. This allows DuckDB Labs to focus on pushing boundaries in the DuckDB software project without chasing exponential growth in sales. While consulting alone is a viable business model for open-source companies, it does not scale well. To address this, DuckDB Labs has acquired shares in Hydra, which connects their success with ours. This way, DuckDB Labs’ founding team joins in the financial success of our partners while allowing us to focus on the technical challenges as an artisanal database company. We welcome all contributions and support to pg_duckdb, large and small as pg_duckdb works towards its first release.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DuckDB version 1.0.0 released</title><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/06/03/duckdb-version-100-released.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DuckDB version 1.0.0 released" /><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/06/03/duckdb-version-100-released</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2024/06/03/duckdb-version-100-released.html"><![CDATA[<p>DuckDB version 1.0.0 has just been released. See the <a href="https://duckdb.org/2024/06/03/announcing-duckdb-100">announcement blog post on duckdb.org</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDB version 1.0.0 has just been released. See the announcement blog post on duckdb.org.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Support Policy for DuckDB</title><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2023/10/02/support-policy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Support Policy for DuckDB" /><published>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/news/2023/10/02/support-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2023/10/02/support-policy.html"><![CDATA[<p>DuckDB Labs is announcing a new support policy for DuckDB and our new flexible commercial support option.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>We are absolutely thrilled how much the DuckDB community has grown, from student projects to enterprise integrations. There are now millions of downloads each month and large growth in the <a href="https://discord.duckdb.org">Discord server</a>, Twitter followers, GitHub stars and so forth. When we started DuckDB back in 2018, we could have not imagined this level of adoption and we are absolutely humbled to see it.</p>

<p>There are some drawbacks to having a large amount of users. The DuckDB project and the company behind the project, DuckDB Labs, are not funded by venture capital by our own choice. We feel investment would force the project direction towards monetization, and we would much prefer keeping DuckDB open and available for as many people as possible. This means that our team cannot grow at the same pace as DuckDB’s usage. This means we have to make some hard choices on how to prioritize our time.</p>

<p><span id="free-support"></span>We would like to be upfront and clarify DuckDB’s support model, and the following policies apply to our free support:</p>

<ul>
  <li><span id="issues-and-discussions"></span> Users can file <a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb/issues">bug reports as issues on GitHub</a> and <a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb/discussions">suggests features on GitHub Discussions</a>.</li>
  <li><span id="response-time"></span> There is no guarantee w.r.t. response time to the reports nor is there any guarantee that issues will be resolved (e.g., fixed) within any time frame.</li>
  <li><span id="volume"></span> We are also unable to support a large volume of support requests from individuals or teams working in the same company.</li>
  <li><span id="apis"></span> We only support the C, Java (JDBC), ODBC, Node.JS, Python and R client APIs as well as the command line shell. The C++ API is intended for internal use and is not designed as a stable user-facing API. The Julia and Swift APIs are rather experimental and not supported.</li>
  <li><span id="extensions"></span> Within the main project, the community support policy only covers the the httpfs, icu, json and parquet extensions. The autocomplete, excel, fts, inet, sqlsmith, tpcds and tpch extensions are not supported.</li>
  <li><span id="internals"></span> We are unable to answer questions about DuckDB internals, e.g., physical operators or storage internals. In general, if an issue cannot be triggered from SQL or one of the supported client APIs, it’s probably out of scope.</li>
  <li><span id="apis-in-scope"></span> We are unable to answer questions regarding all repositories under the duckdb organization, only
<a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb/">duckdb/duckdb</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb-java/">duckdb/duckdb-java</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb-r/">duckdb/duckdb-r</a>,
and
<a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb-node/">duckdb/duckdb-node</a>
are in scope.</li>
  <li><span id="crashes-and-internal-errors"></span> In general, issues that cause crashes (segfault, bus error, abort) and issues that result in internal errors get higher priority.</li>
  <li><span id="platforms"></span> We can only support the following platforms: Windows 10+ on x86_64, macOS latest, Linux x86_64 &amp; aarch64 (mainstream distributions under support by distributor running with glibc). The last three Ubuntu LTS releases are a safe bet (currently: Ubuntu 20.04, 22.04 and 24.04).</li>
  <li><span id="versions"></span> We only support the latest stable version and the bleeding edge version (<a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb/tree/main"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch</a>) of DuckDB.</li>
  <li><span id="architectures"></span> We do not support 32-bit and big-endian architectures.</li>
  <li><span id="debug-builds"></span> Debug builds of DuckDB’s clients and tooling are out of scope.</li>
  <li><span id="discord"></span> Users are welcome to join our <a href="https://discord.duckdb.org">Discord server</a> to engage with the DuckDB community.</li>
</ul>

<p>For support requests that fall outside this support policy, we recommend contacting DuckDB Labs for <a href="https://duckdblabs.com/#support">commercial support options</a>. Commercial support contracts come with guaranteed response time, private issue tracker and private datasets, larger support volume and extended scope with regards to components.</p>

<p>There are several ways that you can help us resolve issues more quickly. The more time you can spend to reduce our team’s workload regarding the issue, the more likely we can help. We sometimes spend an enormous amount of time divining missing information in bug reports like schema, datasets, previous state, environment, etc.</p>

<ul>
  <li><span id="issue-template"></span>Please (please) follow the issue template.</li>
  <li><span id="data-sharing">Please make every effort to provide the data that is triggering the issue. The template advises to include all of the required data in your issue itself. Sometimes this means actually creating a dataset that you can share, which is preferably minimal in size. If you can only reproduce the issue on a proprietary data set, DuckDB Labs offers <a href="https://duckdblabs.com/support/">commercial support</a> where this is possible. We are not able to use proprietary data in the free support tier in general.</span></li>
  <li><span id="test-cases">If possible, include test cases that succeed that are similar to the failure to help pinpoint the problem.</span></li>
  <li><span id="multiple-clients">Try to replicate the issue in multiple clients (CLI preferred).</span></li>
  <li><span id="debugging-issues">Debugging issues is a fantastic way to contribute to DuckDB!</span></li>
  <li><span id="background-information">Providing background information about why you are approaching your task the way you are can help DuckDB Labs suggest workarounds prior to a fix.</span></li>
</ul>

<p>We would like to thank our awesome community and partners in joining us in the journey so far. We are looking forward to continuing our collaboration and delivering new releases DuckDB for everyone to use.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDB Labs is announcing a new support policy for DuckDB and our new flexible commercial support option.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Announcing the MotherDuck Partnership</title><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2022/11/15/motherduck-partnership.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Announcing the MotherDuck Partnership" /><published>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/news/2022/11/15/motherduck-partnership</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2022/11/15/motherduck-partnership.html"><![CDATA[<!--<img height="50" src="https://motherduck.com/_next/static/media/motherduck-logo-black.9a1ead97.svg"/>-->

<p>DuckDB Labs is excited to announce that we are going to be working with <a href="https://motherduck.com">MotherDuck</a> in the coming years to build a modern serverless cloud analytics platform based on DuckDB. DuckDB Labs has entered a long-term strategic partnership with MotherDuck to enrich and extend the DuckDB ecosystem. Jordan Tigani and his amazing founding team have decades of experience pushing the envelope of what is possible in cloud analytics which is why we feel confident to join them in this endeavor.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>When the first ideas that eventually lead to DuckDB were thrown around, we went against the prevailing wisdom in both industry and research that only massive scale and distributed data processing would be the way forward. From our interactions with data practitioners, we became convinced that while massive datasets exist, they are mostly found in organizations that already have the technological expertise to handle them anyway. We bet on efficient and ergonomic single-node analytics, and we are very happy that the MotherDuck team shares this vision, especially given the team’s background.</p>

<p>MotherDuck joins DuckDB Labs’ excellent lineup of partners that includes <a href="https://voltrondata.com/">Voltron Data</a>, <a href="https://relational.ai/">RelationalAI</a>, <a href="https://github.com/looker-open-source/malloy">Google’s Malloy Project</a> and others. DuckDB Labs is not funded by venture capital, its sole owners are the founding team and <a href="https://www.cwi.nl/">CWI</a>. All our revenue comes from partnerships where our partners employ DuckDB in mission-critical roles and contract with DuckDB Labs for close and long-term development collaboration. This allows DuckDB Labs to focus on <a href="https://duckdb.org/2022/11/14/announcing-duckdb-060.html">pushing boundaries</a> in the DuckDB software project without chasing exponential growth in sales.</p>

<p>While consulting alone is a viable business model for Open Source companies, it does not scale well. To address this, DuckDB Labs has acquired shares in MotherDuck, which connects their success with ours. This way, DuckDB Lab’s founding team joins in the financial success of our partners while allowing us to focus on the technical challenges as an artisanal database company.</p>

<p>MotherDuck has also started supporting the <a href="https://duckdb.org/foundation/">DuckDB Foundation</a>: The DuckDB project itself is governed by the non-profit DuckDB Foundation which safeguards the intellectual property and continuity of the DuckDB Project. Its statutes also ensure DuckDB remains Open Source under the MIT license in perpetuity. The foundation appreciates donations from commercial users of DuckDB which organize in the DuckDB user association. User association members are heard for input on the development roadmap and enjoy several other benefits.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDB Labs is excited to announce that we are going to be working with MotherDuck in the coming years to build a modern serverless cloud analytics platform based on DuckDB. DuckDB Labs has entered a long-term strategic partnership with MotherDuck to enrich and extend the DuckDB ecosystem. Jordan Tigani and his amazing founding team have decades of experience pushing the envelope of what is possible in cloud analytics which is why we feel confident to join them in this endeavor.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New CWI Spin-Off Company DuckDB Labs: Solutions for Fast Database Analytics</title><link href="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2021/07/14/spin-off-company-DuckDB-Labs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New CWI Spin-Off Company DuckDB Labs: Solutions for Fast Database Analytics" /><published>2021-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://duckdblabs.com/news/2021/07/14/spin-off-company-DuckDB-Labs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://duckdblabs.com/news/2021/07/14/spin-off-company-DuckDB-Labs.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>TL;DR: CWI researchers Hannes Mühleisen and Mark Raasveldt founded the spin-off company DuckDB Labs, providing services and development for DuckDB. DuckDB is an open-source database management system aimed at efficient data analytics. It is easy to install, works very fast and within running processes. Presently, DuckDB is downloaded about 100.000 times per week.</em></p>

<!--more-->

<p>Companies, governments and academic research groups collect ever more data. These data are stored in large databases and one of the main challenges is to extract new insights from the data as fast as possible. That’s one of the jobs of a database management system.</p>

<p>In 2019 Hannes Mühleisen and Mark Raasveldt, researchers in the Database Architectures research group at Centrum Wiskunde &amp; Informatica (CWI), released the first open-source version of their database management system DuckDB. DuckDB is the first purpose built in-process Online Analytical Processing (OLAP)-database management system.</p>

<p>“DuckDB got its name because I used to have a pet duck”, Mühleisen laughs. “Ducks are amazing animals. They can fly, walk and swim, and they are quite resilient to environmental challenges. So, they are the perfect mascot for a versatile and resilient data management system.”</p>

<p>Now, two years later, DuckDB has become a huge success: it is downloaded about 100.000 times per week, mainly by data scientists and corporate users. “In a world where most successful software has been developed in the corporate sector in the USA, it is remarkable that software coming out of the publicly funded research institute CWI is gaining such a traction”, says Mühleisen.</p>

<p>With the aim of creating an even better system, Mühleisen and Raasveldt just founded DuckDB Labs B.V. as a spin-off company from CWI. The company will act as the environment for innovative projects around DuckDB, to provide further development of the system as well as a platform for support services. Mühleisen emphasizes that DuckDB will still continue to be an Open-Source project under the current permissive MIT licence.</p>

<p>What distinguishes DuckDB from existing database management systems?</p>

<p>Raasveldt: “First of all, DuckDB aims at analytical use cases where it is needed to look at lots of data at the same time. Think about cases where millions of rows have to be aggregated, or where giant tables need to be combined. There are many such use cases in business reporting or in statistical analysis.”</p>

<p>Second, DuckDB runs inside other processes already running on the computer. Raasveldt: “If you do data analysis in Python, DuckDB will run inside Python. That creates the advantage that the data transfer is very quick. Actually, DuckDB is the first in-process OLAP-database system that manages large amounts of data. We call ourselves the ‘SQLite for analytics’. SQLite is the world’s most popular database management system, but it doesn’t do analytics.”</p>

<p>From the practical point of view, DuckDB is ‘lean and mean’. It is a small software package that everybody can easily install and for which no separate server is needed. Finally, DuckDB works fast. This is because DuckDB builds on state-of-the art database research origining from the CWI Datatabase Architecture group. For example, it uses a query processing technique called vectorized execution, which was developed at CWI in 2005.</p>

<p>DuckDB Labs is the newest addition to the list of 28 start-up companies originating at Centrum Wiskunde &amp; Informatica in Amsterdam, a research institute in mathematics and computer science. This tradition of research-based spin-offs is in line with the CWI agenda of converting fundamental research into projects that are beneficial for the society.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: CWI researchers Hannes Mühleisen and Mark Raasveldt founded the spin-off company DuckDB Labs, providing services and development for DuckDB. DuckDB is an open-source database management system aimed at efficient data analytics. It is easy to install, works very fast and within running processes. Presently, DuckDB is downloaded about 100.000 times per week.]]></summary></entry></feed>